um
so Bunty I'm struggling with
overwhelming anxiety
I've been attempting to disassociate
from it via anata practice
but it seems to be intensifying instead
what could I be doing incorrectly in
managing this when it comes to anxiety
really it's it's a symptom
of a problem it's a symptom of
of Untamed mind
that it's kind of becoming self-aware
let's put it that way
like you know the mind that's refusing
to give up sense of control
refusing to give up dependence on
Pleasure but then the world is showing it that
but then the world is showing it that
it's not in control and that the
pleasures that aren't satisfactory so
basically that discrepancy you start to
feel as an anxiety
so really the only the only kind of
lasting way that you could
uh
regain the control of the anxious mind
is through keeping the precepts and
sense restraint until the Mind comes
down so basically anxiety will be
so basically anxiety will be
the result
of you say either circumstances
revealing you the lack of control or you
yourself through uh imposing precepts
and sense restraint
uh that in and of itself would upset the
mind the the wild animal that hasn't been
the the wild animal that hasn't been
tamed and then the anxiety would be its
irrational attempt
to basically to to just cause you pain
to scare you so that you go back to the
old ways of knowing how to deal with
pain which is proliferating further into
the central pleasures
but if you don't give in if you don't go
against the precepts and you don't lose
the sense restraint anxiety will lessen
will come down the mind will stop
resisting because basically the reason why the
because basically the reason why the
mind is anxious it's because it used to
it used to wander around
in all these unchecked pastures
sights sound smell taste touches
and when that is threatened through like
when that is threatened through like
recognition of sickness aging and death
he starts to feel anxious because he
knows nothing else
he knows no other escape from its its
own discomfort
so the point is you don't want to wait
until the circumstances reveal that lack
of control and then make you experience
that anxiety because then you'll be too
late you want to already set the adapter
sensory strain and prevent the Mind from
going there
Let It kick and scream it will have to
come down and when it comes down see
even if he doesn't want to see like like
even if he doesn't want to give up the
anxiety the anxiety will lessen because
the factual discrepancy of what you
assume to be yours and your pastures and
what actually isn't yours and it is in
your pastures that will disappear
because you already started refraining
that mind from from going in those
directions and and eating what he wants
and and other people's crops and the
similars in the sooties
so then even if the mind is not
necessarily thinking about anxiety you
won't experience as much because that
factual existential discrepancy of
taking what it is in yours establishing
yourself upon things that are not in
your control that is lessened so then
that lack of control when experienced or
perceived or remembered cannot undermine
you because you're not standing there on
top of it
because this person's saying he's he's
practically they're practicing anata
well see they are practicing their ideas
of Buddhism
on dama in response to anxiety they want
to get rid of
but I'm saying is if you have anxiety
means the mind is still not tamed and
you don't tame the Mind by introducing
theoretical ideas of anata and and other
contemplations you tame the Mind by
reviewing your behavior and intentional
actions throughout the day
so do you still do you keep the precepts
are you celibate
keep the five precepts with celibacy
do you do that are you containing mine
within that or are you still kind of you
know acting like a householder
then experiencing anxiety on account of
this or that and then trying to use the
dhamma to manage that anxiety
and that's not going to work
because as I said you try you basically
you're you're attacking a symptom
thinking that's really the problem in
itself but it's not the problem is that
the mind is still not tamed nor
contained properly
you you're still acting you're still
taking those domains which are not yours
most likely highly it will be impossible
for you to be established in virtue
uh sensory strain not going into the
other pastures of sensuality that don't
belong to you contain your mind and
experience anxiety
that would be impossible so if there is
anxieties because you are still going
out onto the fields and pastures that
are not yours and immediately see like
imagine you are roaming around someone
else's property and you become
self-aware of that first thing you're
going to experience going to be fear and
anxiety oh what if somebody what if the
owner spots me
what if there is a track what if I'm
being recorded
but if somebody finds this hat uh what
do I do I pretend that this is all mine
I ignore that somebody else owns this
until it's too late now if you don't
pretend you recognize so if there is
anxieties because you're still standing
on someone else's land
what you just said
and there's simile
of
in the Himalayas the king of mountains
they are rugged in uneven zones where
neither monkeys nor humans
can go they are rugged uneven zones
where monkeys can go but not human
beings they are delightful regions where
both monkeys and humans can go
there along the monkey Trails Hunters
set out traps for catchy monkeys
says those monkeys are who are not
foolish and frivolous when they see the
Trap avoid it from afar but a monkey who
is foolish approaches the Trap and
seizes it with his hand he gets caught
there thinking I will free my hand he
sees it with another hand he gets caught
there yeah I will free both my hands he
seizes with his foot you get caught
there thinking I'll free it both free
both my hands and my foot he seizes it
with his other foot he gets caught there
thinking I will free both hands and feet
he applies his mouth to it he gets
caught there
called by the five yeah so the monkey
trapped at Five Points lies they're
screeching he has met with Calamity and
disaster and the hunter can do with him
as he wishes yeah
so and he says so it is because when one
Strays outside one's own Resort into the
domain of others yeah that's what will
happen and and that's like that that
might be hard to accept like you know
for an untrained mind
that has not established itself in
virtue it hasn't gained the right View
telling them that the anxiety you know
that's kind of quite an unpleasant
phenomenon to experience
that that's the result
of certain seemingly insignificant
actions they would kind of require Faith
they would kind of require Faith
initially to accept or if you invest
some decent reasoning you would see that
it's not a far-fetched idea but either
way you're not going to see it
immediately because you are very much deep into the
because you are very much deep into the
the pastures that don't belong to you so
you need to start recognizing signs and
tokens that point out that connect to
your anxiety as a result of it and
that's how you get to understand and
discern for yourself but initially it
might be like I don't see the connection
between my currently you know oppressing
anxiety and the fact that you know I
sometimes say what I want or eat what I
want or or kind of on like there is no
connection between the two because again
like you are proliferated so far into
those pastures that you don't even
really see the extent of it and you
don't see the depth of that kind of
discrepancy of that exposure so you need
to start restraining first in order for
these things to become apparent and same
you might actually make perfect sense
out of it intellectually but if you are
not restraining yourself physically and
actually applying that effort is going
to remain on the level of theory which
means you're still going to be liable to
anxiety that's why fundamentally uh somebody who
that's why fundamentally uh somebody who
has practiced over the internship and is
completely purified from any discrepancy
he's Fearless no fear nor anxiety can
arise in him on account of anything not
because he wants it that way
it's just because uh practice has
resulted in it through through
withdrawing and through withdrawing and
giving up anything that doesn't belong
to you so there's no more discrepancy
for anxiety and fear to arise so it's
like a result of right giving up
so if you ask yourself then I have
anxiety so what do I need to give up
well you start with the precepts do you
keep the precepts like as as your mode
of being as your as your day-to-day
Behavior or is it an occasional thing
that's negotiable you know every now and
then have you taken the real practice
have you taken the real practice
of of
watching your intentions uh not going
against the principles of virtue not
acting not saying by Body by speech uh
anything unwholesome
then do you guard your sense doors from
proliferating into into sensuality are
you taming it and containing it if so
you probably wouldn't have to do it for
that long maybe a year or so and you
will pretty much go beyond anxiety not
in that sense of another hunt but you
would get much better perspective on
what it is you will not be as
overwhelmed like I saw the panel for example can
like I saw the panel for example can
experience anxiety because just like one
of the Fetters but he can't lose
perspective on account of it not
entirely at least because he sees it for
what it is
but somebody with untrained mind that's
still not uh contained and seen rightly
yeah anxiety just turns everything
upside down completely you just you
can't even fathom any other action in
regard to it except getting rid of it
now and that's why it's scary and unpleasant
and that's why it's scary and unpleasant
but if you would have trained yourself
beforehand even that attitude of I need to get rid
even that attitude of I need to get rid
of this right now you'll be able to
contain it and not act out of it
but if you have not been practicing
containing yourself
you will have no means to to to to
establish your mind that level